With talks between the US and Iran
falling apart, there will be renewed
focus this week to say the least on
getting the Strait of Hormuz open and
restoring traffic. Now, nearly all the
attention thus far has been on the
energy part of that, how much oil is
able to transit the bottleneck. But,
there is another key set of commodities
that just as important if not more so. I
don't think people realize how big this
is. We're talking about, yes, an energy
shock, but more importantly, the growing
food shock. Now, the Middle East is a
petroleum powerhouse, which everybody
knows, but that also means a lot of
natural gas production. Now, what the
general public may not know is that with
natural gas comes fertilizer. Roughly
1/3 of the world's seaborne fertilizer
trade goes through Hormuz. About half of
all the traded sulfur comes from the
region, and that's huge for getting
agriculture to grow all around the
planet, not just in the immediate
vicinity. About a quarter of nitrogen
and ammonia. And nitrogen, that's a big
one. As one analyst recently put it,
quote, "It's a long supply chain. If
farmers aren't able to get the urea that
they need, nitrogen, crop yields will
inevitably go lower. Like petroleum, the
scale here is simply enormous." Another
commodity analyst simply said, quote,
"That's why I'm a lot more concerned
about the current crisis than I was when
Russia-Ukraine happened 4 years ago. So,
energy shock, yeah, no doubt. You can
see it its effects already. But, this
food shock, it's going to take a little
bit more time to develop, and if it goes
too far, we aren't just talking about
the price of McDonald's hamburgers. It's
another race against time to fertilize
the world's agriculture.
So, Steve, it's the other shock, right?
We're talking about energy, and it makes
sense that we would focus on oil and
gasoline, or not in the gasoline
necessarily, but downstream of oil. You
know, energy overall, because first
thing you think of when you think of
Iran, Middle East, you think of all of
those oils or oil supply and oil
production facilities around the area.
Plus, you know, tanker traffic that goes
through there, but maybe enough not
enough people realize fertilizer,
energy. I mean, natural gas is a key
component into fertilizer. So, energy
risk areas are also going to be huge
part of the overall food supply chain.
And the food supply chain itself is much
much more diversified geographically, as
well as stretched out in length of time.
So, let's talk about the food shock,
because that's starting to show up in a
lot of different places, too. We're
seeing
fertilizer prices soar, and food prices
are going to be creeping up in the short
run, as well, right?
Absolutely, Jeff. So, you know, we we've
been focused, as you said, on the energy
shock, because this is a real issue for
everyday people all around the world.
And we're now hearing this from
Americans saying, "Wow, this is this is
really painful." And, you know, the risk
we've been talking about is you get
close to the 30-day mark of an energy
shock, and if you can get prices down,
maybe you can actually get past this if
the economy is strong enough. But, as
you said, let's say we do get past that.
What nobody's talking about is the
aftereffect in food. Because if let's
say consumers said, "Okay, you know
what? I'm going to cut back my spending.
I'm going to absorb higher energy costs.
That's going to come down." And then all
of a sudden, they find out their food
costs are surging higher. And then all
of a sudden, you're back to the same
problem, but except it's only worse. You
can't just pump you know, like we can
oil out of the ground and say, "Oh, you
know what? Let's just plant a seed, and
tomorrow it'll be ready to eat." We
can't do that. So, then now the real
risk is we could see this period where
maybe energy prices do come down, and
everyone says, "Hey, we made it
through." And the next thing you know,
everybody around the world is hit with a
food shock. But, the other issue is it's
going to start in a lot of smaller
countries. Here at home, a lot of people
are going to say, "I'm not seeing it
yet. My costs are going up." But, for a
lot of other countries that are really
running out of fuel, and then going to
run out of food, you could see some
major pain start to domino all across
the global economy.
Yeah, that's the thing. The supply chain
where it comes to food and really
agricultural products is more inelastic
than it is for energy. It's not like you
can you know, there's a spare proper
farm sitting around that you can just
activate at a moment's notice. It takes
some time. The the supply chain where it
comes to
even the integrated supply chain that
we've come become used to in the in the
modern economy, where it comes to
agricultural products, it is stretched
out. It takes a long time to react. And
we're not talking about a small thing,
just like on the petroleum side of
things. We're talking about huge
quantities of supplies of very basic
stuff, like fertilizer, like I said,
nitrogen, urea. All of that stuff comes
out of the Middle East, and in fact,
Iran itself is a big a big contributor
to the global supply chain where it
comes to, you know, fertilizer that
needs to go to the farms, and the farms
take the fertilizer and produce crops
out of it. So, if we're blocking the
natural flow of fertilizer from the very
source, it's going to take a little bit
of time to filter its way out.
Unfortunately, on the US side of things,
the spring planting season is already
underway, which means that a lot of
fertilizer supplies have already been
obtained. They're already being used.
So, there's a fair amount of inventory
for US producers, which means primarily
on the US side, the effect will be, as
Steve just said, in terms of higher
cost, which is already not good. I mean,
consumers that are paying higher
gasoline prices will then have to absorb
higher prices at the grocery store.
Economically speaking, we've already
been talking about, you know, the the
so-called K-shaped economy. So, a a
price effect on food in the United
States is is already going to be an
unwelcome
development, as well. But, that's that's
really where it gets more and more
difficult. I mean, we've talked about
the race against time to begin with that
where it comes to the energy shock.
There's also a
an even bigger race against time where
it comes to food, because restoring
fertilizer, I mean, planting seasons are
planting seasons. It's not like we have
a whole lot of flexibility there. So,
when we start talking about the South
American planting season that's
upcoming, we really do have to have all
of the key ingredients, the key
fundamental ingredients in place and and
moving again before we do start to run
into lower crop yields and then food
shortages, like Steve said, in some of
these other places around the world. And
and that's where So, when we when you
talk about the urea prices, nitrogen
prices that affect fertilizer, that's in
the next few months we we're going to
see some some level of re- repricing for
that.
>> Okay. So, you talk about in your notes
this 6-week countdown to an inflection
point. That's what you're referring to,
but that would mean that this is coming
what, next week, 2 weeks from now?
>> We're at 6 weeks now. So, the our
concern was when you look at and this is
more when you think about supplies in
Asia, Korea, Japan, you know, how much
LNG is in reserve, etc. It's about 6
weeks' worth of supply.
So, the 6-week mark, which is where we
are right now, basically, you're going
to see repricing at spot. You know,
Jeff, I think that's a key point, cuz as
we're kind of talking about the energy
shock, you know, usually you see
the kind of drops off, and all of a
sudden either demand goes down or supply
comes back up. But, this is one that
doesn't get fixed right away. Even if
everything did get fixed immediately,
you miss a planting season, or you have
to cut back during the planting season,
and next thing you know, you don't have
enough food. So, yes, not only do you
have prices going up, but you have
perhaps parts of the world that just
aren't going to have the supply of food
they need, because when this starts to
happen, what is the natural reaction is
you're going to hoard. "Oh, I've got
fertilizer? Well, you can't have it.
I've got food? You're not going to get
it. I don't care how much you're willing
to pay, because I need to keep my hands
on this." And then you talk about the
ongoing shock for consumers. You know,
they've really been hoping that energy
prices would come down very quickly.
They're obviously not. And now they're
facing, even if they did, a sustained
demand from higher food prices. And
that's just not going to hit the
consumers. You know, you look at
businesses like McDonald's, who now I
think have a second extra value meal,
Jeff, of even lower prices or probably
smaller portions. And what are you going
to do at that point when you do at that
point when you already know you can't
sell the stuff at normal prices, and
you're going to have to raise prices
again, cuz your costs are going up. They
already know demand's going to go down.
So, for a lot of businesses, too, this
could be the end of the line for them.
What is a Euro Dollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education, and you want
clarity in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our membership
scale with your goals. At Euro Dollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Euro Dollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in a position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore, master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence, click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
Yeah, so you mean you get to the the you
know, for McDonald's, for example, we
talked about that before. McDonald's is
cutting their prices before we even get
to the energy and food shocks. They're
cutting their prices because consumers
can't afford it. So, what happens when
food prices start to rise? And food
prices in this kind of a situation would
tend to be much stickier, which means
food prices aren't going to come back
down very easily. It's going to take
maybe a couple seasons. That's really
the point here. We're talking about the
food shock. It might take a couple of
agricultural seasons for this to really
work its way out. It's sort of like, you
know, going through the snake. The
the shock goes through the head of the
snake, and it takes some time before it
comes out the other end. What comes out
the other end is should be positive, but
it's going to take some time to work
through all of these supply issues. So
McDonald's, McDonald's is already saying
we can't we can't force any higher
prices on our customers, but when their
food costs when their input costs when
they when the prices of their sort of
hamburger patties goes up because you
know all the feed stock you know that
goes into raising cows and whatever else
prices of that goes up and then the
prices of beef which are already high to
begin with they go up even higher, what
is McDonald's going to do? They can't
cut their prices anymore. They were
trying to cut their prices to begin
with. And so you get you get all of
these companies you get all these
businesses all of everything that's
everything that's impacted by the supply
the supply chain and then the supply
issues costs go up costs go up and they
can't pass them along to consumers. The
macroeconomic effect here is pretty
broad as well. So it's not just about
you know maybe some food shortages in
South America coming up for the end of
the year. There's going to be a
tremendous price effect in the entire
global economy has to shift to another
supply issue where it comes to just
food.
So what we're facing is he's kind of I
think what you're saying Jeff is we're
facing sustained demand shocks even if
they start to go away then there's a
second one maybe a third one and for
consumers this is a real problem because
you look at what the market's been
saying is hey inflation goes up rates
have to go up and we've been saying look
that that can happen but it's not
sustainable because consumers will have
to cut back and that's exactly what we
saw in today's CPI report headline
number up 0.9% the core didn't budge and
it makes perfect sense because consumers
are now and this is very quick all of
the way just just in March alone they're
already making a trade-off and we've
been seeing this in the labor market
data you know average hourly earnings
continue to decline but it's even worse
when we look at the lower income and
middle income Americans those workers
they're seeing their incomes are well
below the rate of inflation so the
natural reaction just as we said it
would likely happen is they're going to
have to cut their spending as they cut
their spending that's going to impact
companies like McDonald's who are going
to have to cut hours are going to have
to close stores cut jobs everything's
going to get impacted and then of course
if you look at the reaction from the
market it's going to be like wait a
minute demand is going down inflation is
going to come down the labor markets
weakening and then you're going to see a
massive reversal in rates indicating
exactly what we've been saying is you
can shock an economy once or twice but
if you have sustained shocks and they're
not matched by an increase in wages
there is a point where it's game over.
Yeah it's sort of like a constellation
of consequences here right even on the
you know again here in the United States
where we don't expect to have food
shortages it still leads to
macroeconomic effects that you know the
system has to absorb. And you can kind
of think of it like a boxer who's been
you know in a boxer who's very you know
close to the start of the fight is is
able to withstand the punches that are
coming his way more than one who's been
in a fight you know getting repeatedly
hit and then you get a couple haymakers
on top of it it's much it's a much
different situation. So in in when we're
talking about a food shock plus an
energy shock and we have a weak economy
to begin with it's all of the
adjustments that have to be made on you
know on both a macro as well as micro
scale. I mean consumers
Steve you just that's exactly most
consumers have been struggling to begin
with. The wealthy consumers they've been
spending they've well they've been
cutting back and having to shop at
Walmart but they're still relatively
relatively well off. But then you think
about the all of those who've been
struggling to the point that they can't
even go to the dollar store anymore. So
then now now they have to pay more for
gas and then in a couple months maybe we
start to see the real impact from the
food shock where food prices go up. What
are they going to do? They're going to
do more of what they've been doing so
far. I mean we've we've talked about
uh surveys consumer surveys more
recently after the oil price
gasoline price increases. What have what
have consumers been saying? Well we're
going to cut back on our vacations.
We're not going to travel as much. We're
not going to drive as much. We're going
to try to cut back where we can. We're
not going to eat out as much. Uh that
was before every you know Americans got
the sense of what's going to come as far
as food prices. They're not going to eat
out as much just because they their
energy costs and gasoline costs go up.
What happens when gasoline still
relatively high but then the cost of
eating out itself goes skyrocketing
upward too. Like I said we talked about
this before we started recording. This
is not going to be good for Taco Bell
and McDonald's. So even if we don't face
specifically food shortages there are
going to be disruptions that could
potentially lead to all sorts of
negative outcomes all across the
first of all the economic landscape but
also the geographic landscapes as well.
Yeah Jeff and economically it kind of
sounds like what you're saying here is
there's absolutely going to be no
winners because we already know we're at
the point where as we've talked about
consumers cannot afford higher prices
they they've made that very clear and
now we're starting to see it in their
spending habits. Now one thing we don't
know this probably the big variable is
we do know that consumers have gotten
gotten larger tax refund checks. Now how
they're going to use it we don't know.
Are they going to you know spend freely
into the economy are they going to say
wait a minute I got to hang on to this
and then spread it out to absorb these
higher prices for the things they need.
We don't know what the sustainability is
of the average consumer when you tack on
the stimulus. What we do know is when
the stimulus runs out things are going
to drop off. But for the bigger problem
here and you look at how this thing just
spirals out of control is businesses now
are facing the fact is we're going to
have to raise prices. We don't have a
choice because our input costs are going
up. We don't really have any margin to
really cut anymore because we've already
absorbed as much of the tariffs we've
absorbed as much as this. We have to
stay profitable at some level because
we'd be out of business. Now the problem
is as we know as prices go up there's
going to be an equal reaction of demand
dropping and then what are businesses
going to do? They're going to cut hours
and they're going to cut jobs and then
as more people are out of work or have
less work well their spending is going
to go down and then next thing you know
what are businesses going to have to do
is say well demand dropped I'm going to
have to lay off more people and that is
the risk that we're facing is the longer
this goes on it's it's not you know but
hey businesses are going to make a bunch
of money cuz their price went up. No
because demand is going to go down.
That's the issue they're facing. The
question then becomes is if we know
that's the likely path where is the
tipping point? We can't see that just
yet but it almost doesn't seem like it's
a whole lot far off in the horizon.
Yeah that's I think the overall
question. I think it's what most people
want us to answer at least want to you
know the question
What is that tipping point? Um for
energy sector we've talked about that.
Let's talk about the food tipping point
for example. Uh some experts have said
that the tipping point for nitrogen
supplies for example
uh maybe two to three months. Uh there's
probably enough of enough supply there
even though we're talking about massive
amounts of of quantity that are taken
off the marketplace just because the
Strait of Hormuz isn't working. You know
what do I say 30% about roughly a third
of global supply goes through Hormuz or
comes out of the Middle East some in
some fashion.
So maybe a month or two before nitrogen
supplies really start to run down. And
in anyway no matter what happens even if
we start to run through the inventories
that's going to that's going to create a
price effect because as inventories get
drawn down people start to scramble to
replace the inventory so the price of
whatever it is that's being drawn down
that's going to continue to rise even
faster. So
the more the longer this goes even if
there is enough inventory to get through
say the the current planting season
there's still going to be a price effect
because as as inventories get drawn down
people start to panic to try to
replenish them to make sure they have
enough there. So Even we're already a
month into this a little bit over a
month a month and a week into this. So
we're already getting closer to that
margin to begin with at least according
to most experts on the logistics of
moving fertilizer up through the
agricultural supply chain. So when you
get to two months to three months that's
when you start to get the more drastic
decisions among agricultural producers
the farmers themselves have to change up
their farm supplies or the what they're
actually going to farm in that
particular season. Like I said that's
where it may not match with demand and
then farmers are not actually responding
to demand in the economy they're they're
making cost benefit calculations. Do I
have enough nitrogen available to plant
the thing that's going to pay me that's
going to give me the most profitability?
If the cost of nitrogen is too high
maybe I have to switch to something that
the market doesn't really want but it's
easier to plant it's it's less nitrogen
intensive. So
again there's a
we get to two to three months on the on
the fertilizer supply issue that's where
you start to see more drastic changes
and it's going to take some time for
them to work through the overall economy
and it is as it already is we're already
like I said a month into this. You got
to believe that's at the margins already
some of agricultural producers that
maybe were not ahead of the game who
didn't have fertilizer supplies secured
or at least their full need for the full
planting planting season they didn't
have that completely on on
in hand already
you can start to see some changes in
behavior that then
the the entire global supply chain has
to work around. And so then we're back
into a similar situation like 2022
where food prices got to be
uncomfortably high in a lots of regions
around the world and where this gets to
be really um
an even bigger problem is because we're
talking about the entire Middle East
which is a much bigger contribution of
fertilizer it can impact more areas than
just say you know like Russia Ukraine
was focused on a lot Europe really took
that one hard some places in the Middle
East um with such a dis the size of the
disruption we're talking about here it's
going to impact much more of the world
in terms of prices more directly and
then we'll see where it goes as far as
physical shortages.
Right Jeff cuz there are countries that
that don't have our ability to grow a
massive amount of crops they're relying
on imports and I think that's going to
be an issue not only those countries
really being hammered by energy prices
you're seeing the fact shortages lines
at gas stations you're seeing airports
that are you know running out of jet
fuel and now what happened is let's say
that they can't get enough food. I mean,
at this point, you're you're talking
about seeing a lot of small economies
just completely crumble. So, if people
are looking kind of what an inflection
point is, I wouldn't be looking here at
the US at all because I think you're
right. I don't think we're going to see
an impact, and if we were to see an
impact, it's so far down the road that,
you know, by that point, there's going
to be other issues in the economy. But,
to see where this is really going to hit
on a global scale, if we start to see
some small countries just kind of, you
know, crumble into massive recessions
because of lack of food and, you know,
lack of energy, I think that is a domino
that once it starts tipping, it's going
to roll through the entire global supply
chain and then impact the world all at
once.
And let's be clear though, that's that's
sort of the worst-case scenarios down
the road. But, I mean, that's the point.
Um,
you know, the time is running out. The
clock is ticking here. We've got to get
this thing going to have any chance to
avoid some of those bad scenarios. But,
at the very least, to wrap this up, at
the very least, we should expect a some
significant price impact on food prices
even here in the United States. That's
going to happen. It's going to happen
more and more as we go further along.
Even if the Strait of Hormuz opens
tomorrow and nitrogen starts to flow,
there are already things that have taken
place and, you know, disruptions that
have happened that it's going to cause
some short-run impact that's going to
stick around in the intermediate term.
So, what we're really talking about for
the US economy is the the backlash for
food prices. Then, after that, it gets a
little bit more dicey around the rest of
the world because not only are you
talking about rising energy as well as
food prices, you also have the prospect
of food shortages, which just makes a
bad situation that much worse. So, I
think what we're saying here at the very
least is there's a price effect that's
going to come and it's still it's still
working its way through. Um, and then,
beyond that, it depends on how long it
really takes to get the the Strait of
Hormuz opened and fertilizer along with
petroleum flowing through it. But, the
longer this goes, the more severe
consequences, the chances of those
taking place really do go up. And let's
face it, I mean, Steve, you and I have
talked about this, you know, for for
quite some time already.
The world is not in good shape to be
able to withstand something like this
taking place. So, even if food prices
don't go to the maximum, if just food
prices go up, say, you know, some
substantial amount, but it's not it's
not catastrophic, it can still produce
some some really negative consequence in
the real economy because as we keep
going along, less jobs, less incomes,
less able to withstand something like
this, the more these things happen, the
greater the chances it leads to just a
cascading failure.